Guide to the James A. Healy Collection of Irish literature, 1870-1976
Department of Special Collections
James A. Healy Collection of Irish literature,
1870-1976
Special Collections M0273
Healy, James A. (James Augustine), d.1975.
8 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of James A. Healy, 1975, in memory of his wife, Josephine Healy. Works written by James Brendan Connolly, copyright held by Miss Brenda E. Connolly.
Scope and Content
This collection of books, letters, and other manuscripts was amassed by James A. Healy from his early days as a bibliophile in the thirties until his death in 1975. Its greatest strengths are in the areas in which he had personal contacts: his friendship with Oliver St. John Gogarty; his extended correspondence with Elizabeth C. Yeats and George Yeats, from whom he obtained all the Dun Emer and Cuala Press books (a great number of which were inscribed by their authors or by W. B. Yeats); a very fine selection of Cuala Press greeting cards and prints; and his contacts with Ernest Boyd, Richard Campbell, and Irene Haugh, which brought him AE's letters to those recipients and some of his unpublished lectures.
The interest of the collection extends further, to figures who were primarily artists rather than writers, such as Paul Henry and W. B. Yeats' father, brother, and two sisters, and entrepreneurs and actors such as the Fay Brothers and Dudley Digges. There is a handful of interesting letters from James Joyce, John M. Synge, Maud Gonne, and George Moore. In addition, from the critic Ernest Boyd's estate Healy obtained letters from Irish writers prompted by Boyd's research for his book, The Irish Literary Renaissance (1916).
Arrangement Note
PART ONE
The letters have been arranged alphabetically by writer; within each writer's section they are placed alphabetically by recipient. Any MSS or printed articles by, or clippings about, each individual immediately follow letters by him or her.
The numerous insignificant letters from libraries, publishers, etc. have been arranged alphabetically in folders labelled A, B, C, and so forth, but are not further itemized. Letters from unknown individuals to significant figures such as AE are, however, itemized separately, as are a few letters from unknown individuals to Healy which contain interesting references.
At the end of the manuscript section of the collection, Box 16 contains the Dun Emer and Cuala Press printed materials (other than books and oversize prints); a folder of Elizabeth C. Yeats' letters and enclosed announcements, the gift of Mr. J. Richard Blanchard; and a copy of the Cuala Press keepsake printed for the opening of the Stanford exhibition in 1976.
Photographs are listed here, but are maintained in a separate departmental Photograph File.
Only the most important material from the substantial Vertical File of miscellaneous clippings has been catalogued.
A Cross-Reference Listing, of significant figures written to or about, is also provided.
PART TWO
This covers all the Dun Emer and Cuala Press books and broadsides, with their inscriptions transcribed at length, and the books of particular interest from other presses more briefly. They are combined in one listing, alphabetized by author. Magazines and auction catalogues are also itemized briefly.
LIST OF ABBREVIATIONS
CORRESPONDENTS
EAB Ernest A. Boyd
JC Joseph Campbell
RC Richard Campbell
AC Austin Clarke
EC Eileen Colum
PC Padraic Colum
D Lord Dunsany
OG Oliver St. John Gogarty
LG Lady Gregory
IH Irene Haugh
JAH James A. Healy
PH Paul Henry
JJ James Joyce
EFK Eugene F. Kinkead
WKM W. K. Magee
MM Michael Monahan
GM George Moore
SO'S Seumas O'Sullivan
LR Lennox Robinson
AR Anna Russell
AE George Russell
[N.B. alphabetized as R]
GBS George Bernard Shaw
JS James Stephens
JMS John M. Synge
KT Katherine Tynan
ECY Elizabeth C. Yeats
GY George Yeats
Jack BY Jack B. Yeats
JBY John B. Yeats
LY Lily Yeats
MCY Mary Cottenham Yeats
WBY William B. Yeats
PLACES
B Boston/Brookline
D Dublin
Dm Dundrum, Co. Dublin
G Greystones, Co. Wicklow
L London
NYC New York City
R Rathfarnham, Dublin
SF San Francisco
OTHER
AIHS American-Irish Historical Society
CP Cuala Press
DE Dun Emer Press
TECHNICAL TERMS
AL autograph letter
ALS autograph letter, signed
TLS typed letter, signed
TLc typed letter, carbon of
APCS autograph postcard, signed
ANS autograph note, signed
ADS autograph document, lecture, poem, etc., signed
TD typed document, etc.
PD printed document, etc.
AtelS autograph telegram, signed
Tmimeo typed mimeograph
trans. transcript, i.e. typed copy of an original item (often indicates an important item
Pc photocopy/xerox (only used here when there is no original of the item in the collection)
() number of additional photocopies, xeroxes, or carbons of original item
w/a with annotations
w/cov. with cover
enc. enclosing/enclosures
s indicates plural, at end of rubric
EDITORIAL PROCEDURES
Undated letters are placed at the end of any given folder, except when there is strong circumstantial evidence for their being placed earlier.
Dates in brackets, [], are transcribed from the postmark or an annotation by another reader such as JAH, or deduced from internal evidence.
The number of pages, not sheets, is given after the dash in each entry. Thus a single sheet, written on both sides, with two photocopies of it, would be entered as ALS - 2 (2).
Dates are given in the following form: month/day/year (i.e. English-style dating has been changed to American style).
Photocopies of an original that is in the collection are placed at the end of their folder, separated by Perma-life paper.
Container List
- CATALOGUE OF MANUSCRIPT, BOXES 1-16
  - A (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Not listed individually
  - ABERDEEN (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Aberdeen, [Lord] (D) to ECY, 11-27-13., ALS - 4 w/ AL postscript - 4
    - Aberdeen, Isobel (D) to ECY, 3-3-14., ALS - 4
  - ALDINGTON, RICHARD (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Aldington, Richard (Padworth, Berks.) to Editor, New York World, 11-7-24., TLS - 1 and trans.
  - ALLGOOD, SARA (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Allgood, Sara (NYC) to JAH, 4-7-40., TLS - 1
    - Allgood, Sara (Hollywood) to Miss Russell, 2-18-49., ALS - 1
    - Clipping, 1-31-39
  - ALLINGHAM, WILLIAM (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Allingham, W. (NP) to [J.T. Fields], ND., ANS - 1
    - Allingham, W. (Chelsea, London) to My dear Knowles, 4-16-1878., ALS - 3
    - Allingham, W. (NP), article, Shelley's `Lines to an Indian Air', 1-29-1883., ADS - 2
  - AMERICAN-IRISH HISTORICAL SOCIETY DINNER, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Seating list, ND., PD - 1 w/a
    - 42 letters of acceptance
    - [?],speech about Judge O'Brien., TDc - 7
  - ARMSTRONG, H.F.; ARNOLD, SIDNEY; AYRES, H.M. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Armstrong, H.F. (NYC) to AE, 1-26-28., TLS - 2
    - Arnold, Sidney (S. Chingford) to JAH, 1-31-56., TLS - 2
    - Arnold, Sidney (S. Chingford) to JAH, 12-3-57., TLS - 2
    - Arnold, Sidney (Dun Laoghaire) to JAH, 4-21-58., TLS - 1
    - Ayres, H. M. (NYC) to [AE], 2-3-28., TLS - 1
  - B (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - BARLOW, JANE (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Barlow, Jane (D) to Mr. Everson, 9-2-?, ALS - 2
    - Barlow, Jane (D) to Mr. Rideing, 12-31-01., ALS - 1
    - Barlow, Jane (Wicklow) to Mr. Rideing, 2-7-17., ALS - 1
    - Barlow, Jane (D) to Mr. Rideing, 9-24-?, ALS - 2
    - Barlow, Jane (D) to Mr. Rideing, 10-27-?, ALS - 3
    - Barlow, Jane (D) to Mr. Rideing, 11-29-?, ALS - 3
    - Barlow, Jane (D) to Mr. Rideing, 11-30-?, ALS - 1
    - Barlow, Jane (D) to Mr. Rideing, 12-5-?, ALS - 1
    - Barlow, Jane (D) to Mr. Young, 9-11-?, ALS - 2
    - Barlow, Jane (D) to Dear Sir, 1-28-?, ALS - 1
    - Barlow, Jane (D) to Dear Sir, 2-11-?, ALS - 2
    - Barlow, Jane (D) to Dear Sir, 2-29-?, ALS - 1
    - Barlow, Jane (D) to Dear Sir, 12-26-?, ALS - 1
    - Barlow, Jane (D) to Dear Sir, ND., ALS - 1
  - BARRY, RICHARD (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Barry, Richard: 5 letters, 1943-46,to JAH; 17 letters, 1943-54,between various correspondents on his book Mr. Rutledge of South Carolina; clippings and flyers
  - BENNETT, ARNOLD (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bennett, Arnold, review of Ervine, St. John's The Wayward Man, 12-19-27., ADS - 2, w/ auction notice
    - Bennett, Arnold, review of Norah Hoult's Time Gentlemen Time, 4-16-30., ADS - 2, w/ auction notice
    - Bennett, Arnold, essay, Irish Literature, 8-9-30., ADS - 2, w/ auction notice
    - Bennett, Arnold, essay on George Moore, 10-27-29., ADS - 2 w/ auction notice
    - Bennett, Arnold, review of George Moore's Confessions of a Young Man, 3-17-28., ADS - 2 w/ auction notice and 2 trans.
    - Bennett, Arnold, essay, Plays. Shaw, Wilde et al, 2-14-27., ADS - 2 w/ auction notice
    - Bennett, Arnold, essay on Wilde's The Importance of Being Earnest, 6-26-27., ADS - 2 w/ auction notice
    - Copy of listing of Bennett AMSS on Irish literature in C.A. Stonehill catalogue, 1938., TD - 2
  - BOURGEOIS (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Bourgeois, Maurice (Paris) to EAB, 6-27-16., APCS - 1
    - [Bourgeois?], pencil sketch of St. Boyd from memory, signed Saphier
  - BOWERS (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Bowers, Claude S. (NYC) to RC, 12-12-27., TLS - 1
    - Bowers, Claude S. (NYC) to AE, 2-3-28., TLS - 1
  - BOYD (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - EAB (NYC) to JAH, 6-30-37., TLS - 1
    - EAB (Woods Hole, Mass.) to JAH, 7-17-37., ALS - 2
    - EAB (NYC) to JAH, 8-5-37., TLS - 1
    - EAB (NYC) to JAH, 9-25-42., TLS w/a - 1 w/cov.
    - EAB (NYC) to JAH, 3-17-44., TLS - w/cov.
    - EAB (NYC) to JAH, 7-7-46., ALS - 1 w/cov.
    - EAB (NYC) to Mr. Spingarn, 8-27-24., TLS - 2 w/cov.
    - EAB, notes on Irish politics and arts, ND., AD - 2
    - EAB, clipping of letter to editor of Sat. Rev. Lit. re Ulysses, 3-3-34 -, 1
    - EAB, the Gay Twenties re Harold Stearns' The Street I Know, tearsheets - 4
    - [EAB], clippings re death of - 4, (some duplicates)
    - 3 envelopes to EAB in unidentified hands: Paris, Jan. 1915?; D 1-20-18; D 3-22-21
    - Boyd, Madeleine (NYC) to JAH, 1-5-47., ALS - 3 w/cov.
    - [Boyd, Madeleine], clippings re - 6 (some duplicates)
  - BOYD: MP PURCHASES (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - JAH's lists of books from EAB's library, TD - 3 and pencil notes, AD - 7
    - Transcripts of letters purchased (but originals sold), now placed in Stephens, AE, and WBY folders, q.v.
  - BRETT (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Brett, G. P. (NYC) to OG, 2-9-33., TLS - 2, enc. list of OG's poems (one added in OG's hand), TD - 2
    - Brett, G.P. (NYC) to OG, 2-21-33., TLS - 2
  - BUCHANAN (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Buchanan, Robert W. (So. Hampstead) to Charles Cartwright, ND., ALS - 1
    - Buchanan, Robert W. (Glasgow) to Le Chevalier de Chatelain, ND., ALS - 4
    - Buchanan, Robert W. (L?) to Miss Alicia Leith, 6-17-?., ALS - 1
    - Buchanan, Robert W. (So. Hampstead) to Editor of The Academy re The Outcast, 11-2-1891., ALS - 3
  - BYNNER (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Bynner, Witter (Santa Fe) to OG, 1-28-51., TLS w/a - 1
    - Bynner, W. (NP) poem, Evening Prayer, [before 6-2-44]., TDcS w/a To Oliver Gogarty - 1
    - Bynner, W., (NP) poem, Seed, ND., TDcS w/a - 1
    - Bynner, W., (NP) poem, The Hand, ND., TDcS w/a - 2
    - Bynner, W., (NP) poem, Collect, ND., TDcS w/a O. St. J. G - 1
    - Bynner, W., (NP) poem, Nocturne, ND., TDcS w/a -1
  - BYRNE, DONN (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Byrne, Donn, poem, The Chap, a parody of OG's The Ship on same page., Trans: TDc - 2
    - Wetherbee, Winthrop Jr., A Bibliography of Donn Byrne from NYPL, 1948-49 -, 8
    - AIHS Recorder, Donn Byrne, 2-2-39 -, 3
    - Clipping, Ten Years and a Million Dollars
    - 3 publishers' circulars on Byrne's novels -, 6
  - BYRNE, JAMES (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Byrne, James (NYC) to AE, 1-28-29., TL - 1
  - C (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - CAMPBELL, JOSEPH (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - JC (D) to George Bainton, 12-15-13., ALS - 1
    - JC (D) to EAB, 1-15-14., ALS - 3
    - JC (D) to EAB, 8-18-15., ALS - 5
    - JC (Wicklow) to EAB, 11-28-16., ALS - 1
    - JC (NYC) to JAH, [4-17-38]., APC - 1 and printed announcement PC - 1 w/cov.
    - JC (NYC) to JAH, 11-29-38., TLS - 3
    - JC (NYC) to JAH, 12 -1-38., APCS - 1 w/cov.
    - JC (NYC) to JAH, 12-15-38, ALS - 4 w/cov.
    - JC (NYC) to JAH, [12-22-38]., ALS - 1 w/ cov.
    - JC (NYC) to JAH, 1-2-39., APCS - 1 w/cov.
    - empty cover, 1-8-39
    - JC (Enniskerry) to Gene Kinkead, 2-19-40., Trans: TL - 3 (3)
  - CAMPBELL, RICHARD: GENERAL CORRESPONDENCE (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - RC (NP) to American Farm Fdn. Org. Comm., 4-28-31., TL - 1
    - Constituent Agreement Creating the AFF., Tmimeo D - 13
    - A Proposal for an AFF., TmimeoD - 6
    - RC (NP) to James Byrne, 1-22-25., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP) to James Byrne, 12-1-27., TLc - 1
    - RC (NYC) to E.F. Carry, 11-13-27., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP) to E.F. Carry, 3-27-28., TLc - 3
    - RC (NP) to E.F. Carry, 4-10-28., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP) to PC, 11-24-33., TLc w/a - 1
    - RC (NP) to Clara Cudahy, 5-31-28., TLc - 1
    - RC (NYC) to E. A. Cudahy, 11-30-27., TLc - 2 (2)
    - RC (NP) to J.S. Cullinan, 1-3-24., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP) to J.S. Cullinan, 4-2-24., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP) to J.S. Cullinan, 4-22-24., TLc -2
    - RC (NP) to J.S. Cullinan, 7-30-24., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP) to J.S. Cullinan, 4-8-26., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP) to J.S. Cullinan, 5-1-28., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP) to J.S. Cullinan, 5-31-28., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP) to J. S. Cullinan, 5-31-28., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP) to J. S. Cullinan, 6-22-28., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP) to J. S. Cullinan, 12-21-28., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP) to J. S. Cullinan, 2-15-30., TLc - 3
    - RC (NP) to J. S. Cullinan, 11-6-33., TLc - 1 enc. receipt
    - RC (NP) to J. S. Cullinan, 11-16-33., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP) to J. S. Cullinan, 9-14-34., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP) to J. S. Cullinan, 9-12-35., TLc - 3
    - RC (NP) to E. L. Doheny, 4-13-26., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP) to E. L. Doheny, 12-27-27., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP) to James A. Farrell, 6-27-28., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP) to James M. Kerwin, 1-9-25., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP) to Mr. Lecron, 11-21-34, TLc - 2
    - RC (NP) to Charmian London, 11-24-33., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP) to George MacDonald, 6-11-28., TLc - 3
    - RC (NP) to W. C. McBride, Inc., 1-3-29., TLc - 2
    - RC (NYC) to S. T. O'Ceallaigh, T.D., 2-25-32., TLc -3
    - RC (NP) to Ruth Pedersen, 11-22-34., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP) to Ruth Pedersen, 11-27-34., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP) to Ruth Pedersen, 12-11-34., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP) to James J. Phelan, 6-23-30., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP) to Mary Harriman Rumsey, 7-11-28., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP) to MHR, 6-13-33., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP) to MHR, first letter of 12-14-33, TLc -1 enclosing second letter, TLc -1
    - RC, printed invitation to meet Mr. George Wm. Russell -, 1
    - RC (NP) to P. J. Shouvlin, 7-1-24., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP) to PJS, 3-29-26., TLc -1
    - RC (NP) to PJS, 5-27-28., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP) to Cornelius J. Sullivan, 5-23-28., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP) to CJS, 5-29-28., TLc -1
    - RC (NP) to Mary Sullivan, 4-25-32., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP) to Theodore Tetse, ND., TDc - 1
    - RC (NP) to Henry A. Wallace, 11-27-34., TLc w/a -1
    - RC (NP) to MLW, 12-10-34., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP) to MLW, 12-16-34., AteleS - 1
    - RC (NP) to MLW, 12-17-34., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP) to MLW, 1-17-35., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP) to MLW, 3-8-35., TLc - 4
    - RC (NP) to MLW, 5-13-35., TLc - 1
    - RC, Farewell to AE, broadcast script, 7-23-35., TDS - 3
    - [RC?], address to Mission of our Lady of the Rosary, ND., TDc w/a - 6
    - In Memoriam for RC., PD - 4 (2)
    - Clippings re RC -, 5
    - Clipping by B, Letters of the Scattered Brotherhood, w/ ANS by RC on calling card, attached
    - Trans. of clipping re gamecocks -, 1
    - Invitation to dedication ceremony of RC Memorial., PD - 1
  - CAMPBELL, RICHARD, TO OG (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - RC (NP), 1-17-29., TLc - 4
    - RC (NP), 2-23-29., TLc - 3
    - RC (NP), 5-2-33., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP), 5-15-33., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP), 5-25-33., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP), 6-21-33., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP), 6-30-33., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP), 7-5-33., TLc -1
    - RC (NP), 11-22-33., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP), 9-25-34., TLc - 4, w/ trans.
    - RC (NP), 8-16-35., TLc - 3
    - RC (NP), ND.TNS re Yeats and AE's funeral -, 1
    - RC (NYC) [after 8-27-35]., ALS - 17
  - CAMPBELL, RICHARD, TO AE (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - RC (NP), 6-18-24., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP), 3-16-26., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP), 4-16-26., TLc -1
    - RC (NP), 10-17-27., Trans. of telegram - 1
    - RC (NP), 10-18-27., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP), 10-31-27., Telegram - 1
    - RC (NP), 11-9-27., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP), 11-10-27., Telegram - 1
    - RC (NP), 11-12-27., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP), 11-21-27., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP), 11-23-27., Telegram - 1
    - RC (NP), 12-21-27., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP), 5-24-28., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP), 6-26-28., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP), 8-2-28., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP, 12-1-28., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP), 12-11-28., TLc - 4
    - RC (NP), 12-18-28., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP), 12-18-28., Telegram - 1
    - RC (NP), 1-2-29., TLc - 3
    - RC (NP), 1-15-29., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP), 1-28-29., TLc - 4
    - RC (NP), 2-11-29., TLc - 3
    - RC (NP), 2-19-29., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP), 2-27-29., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP), 3-8-29., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP), 3-12-29., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP), 3-14-29., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP), 3-28-29., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP), 4-2-29., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP), 4-15-29., TLc - 4
    - RC (NP), 4-23-29., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP), 5-8-29., TLc - 3
    - RC (NP), 5-13-29., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP), 5-21-29., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP), 1-16-30., TLc - 3
    - RC (NP), 1-23-30., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP), 2-3-30., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP), 2-11-30., TLc - 4
    - RC (NYC), 3-3-30., Telegram - 1
    - RC (NP), 3-3-30., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP), 3-4-30., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP), 1-26-32., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP), 2-23-32., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP), 3-22-32., TLc - 4
    - RC (NP), 3-30-32., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP), 4-16-32., TLc - 4
    - RC (NP), 6-6-32., TLS w/a - 6
    - RC (NP), 8-4-32., ALS - 4 [probably a draft of next letter]
    - RC (NP), 8-4-32., TLc - 7 (2)
    - RC (NP), 5-2-33., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP), 6-7-33., TLc - 3
    - RC (NP), 10-31-34., TLc - 3
    - RC (NYC), 11-2-34., Telegram - 1
    - RC (NP), 11-26-34., Telegram - 1
    - RC (NP), 1-29-35., TLc - 1
    - RC (NP), 2-11-35., TLC - 1
    - RC (NP), 5-13-35., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP), 6-18-35., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP), untitled TD [Farewell to AE] -, 3 (4 drafts in varying stages)
    - RC (NP), 8-13-35to Mrs. Diarmuid Russell., TLc - 2
    - RC (NP), 8-26-35to Diarmuid Russell., TLc - 2
  - CASEMENT, ROGER (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Casement, Roger (Philadelphia) to EAB, 8-4-14., pc of ALS - 2
    - Casement, Roger (Munich) to Gaffney, Saturday morning., Trans. of ALS - 2
    - [re Casement] Joseph Conrad (Orlestone, Kent) to John Quinn, 5-24-16., Trans. of extract - 1 (1)
    - Casement, Roger, address given at Forrest Theatre, Phila., 8-2-14., Trans. of AD: TDc - 9
    - Casement, Roger (Pentonville), Last Message to Ireland, 8-2-16., pc [of trans?]: TD - 1 w/a
    - 6 clippings and extracts.
  - CHILDERS, M.A. (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Childers, M.A. (D) to OG, 8-11-20., ANS - 1 (1)
  - CLARKE, AUSTIN (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - AC (D) to JAH, 10-2-57., TLS - 2 w/cov.
    - AC (D) to Seamus O'Sullivan, [1916]., ALS - 1
    - AC (St. Albans) to Seamus O'Sullivan, 2-6-36., TLS - 2
    - AC (Templeogue) to Seamus O'Sullivan, 8-11-37., TLS - 1
    - AC (Templeogue) to Seamus O'Sullivan, 8-18-37., TLS - 1
    - AC (Templeogue) to Seamus O'Sullivan, 10-27-37., TLS - 1 w/cov.
    - AC (L) to [Gaelic term], ND., ALS - 1
    - AC (Templeogue), review of The Course of Irish Verse by Robert Farren (1948), ND., TD w/a - 3
    - AC, review of The Renaissance of Irish Poetry by David Morton, ND.., TD w/a - 8
      See also Vertical File for many clippings
    - Clarke, Austin, review of U. O`Connor's The Times I've Seen, 3-22-64.Clipping from N.Y. Times Book Review -, 1
  - COLLES, W.M.; COLUM, EILEEN (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Colles, W. Morris (L) to Standish O'Grady, 1-6-1894, pc of ALS -1
    - Colles, W. Morris (Deal) to [Gaelic term?], ND., pc of ALS -1
    - EC (D) to JAH, 3-16-40, TLS - 2 w/cov.
    - EC (D) to JAH, 8-14-40, TLS - 1 w/cov., enc. receipt 8-12-40, ADS - 1
  - COLUM, MARY (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Colum, Mary (NYC) to OG [3-2-43]., ALS - 2 w/cov.
    - [Colum, Mary?], biographical note re PC, ND., AD - 1
    - Colum, Mary, Memories of Yeats in SR, 2-25-39
    - 3 reviews of her books
    - Clippings re her death -, 2
  - COLUM, PADRATIC (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - PC (D) to EAB, 6-2-13., TLS - 1
    - PC (D) to EAB, 4-22-14., ALS - 5
    - PC (NYC) to EAB, 1-27-15., TLS - 1
    - PC (NYC) to EAB, 1-29-15., TLS - 1
    - PC (NYC) to EAB, 2-4-15., ALS - 1
    - PC (Chicago) to EAB, 5-1-15., ALS - 2
    - PC (Pittsburgh) to EAB, 7-14-15., ALS - 3
    - PC (W. Cummington, Mass.) to EAB, 10-6-15., TLS - 1
    - PC (NYC) to EAB, 4-25-16., ALS - 3
    - PC (NYC) to EAB, 7-18-16., ALS - 3
    - PC (NYC) to EAB, 8-17-16., ALS - 2
    - PC (NYC) to EAB, 12-1-18., ALS - 3
    - PC (NYC) to EAB, 3-28-19., TLS - 1
    - PC (Colorado Springs) to EAB, 12-20-19, APCS - 1
    - PC (Colorado Springs) to EAB, 7-19-23, APCS - 1
    - PC (N.H.) to EAB, 9-18-23, TLS - 1
    - PC (New Canaan, Conn.) to EAB, 10-18-26, ALS - 2 w/cov.
    - PC (Rome) to EAB, 11-12-?, APCS - 1
    - PC (NYC) to EAB, ND., ALS - 1
    - PC (NYC) to EAB, ND., TLS - 2
    - PC (NYC) to EAB, ND., ALS - 1
    - PC (NYC) to EAB, ND., ALS - 4
    - PC (NYC) to EAB, ND., TLS - 1
    - PC (Colorado Springs) to Madeleine Boyd, 6-11-21, APCS - 1
    - PC (Colorado Springs) to Madeleine Boyd, 6-24-21., APCS - 1
    - PC (Miami) to Richard [Campbell?], 3-9-35, LS - 1
    - PC (Nice) to John Gallagher, 8-14-33., TLS - 1
    - PC (NYC) to JAH, 1-11-40., TNS - 1 w/cov.
    - PC (NYC) to JAH, 5-5-41, TPCS - 1
    - PC (NYC) to JAH, 5-1-53., TLS - 1 w/cov.
    - PC (NYC) to JAH, 5-6-53., TLS - 2 w/cov.
    - PC (Donnybrook) to F.A. King, 11-1-10., TLS - 1
    - PC (Donnybrook) to F.A. King, 1-4-11., ALS - 1
    - PC (Pittsburgh) to F.A. King, Sunday., ALS - 1
    - PC (NYC) to Seumas [JAH annotates this as James Stephens -?] 5-22-24., ALS - 4
    - PC (NP) poem, Arthur Grifftih, 8-13-/18-22., TDcS w/a - 3
    - PC Pf`ttsung), poem, The Ballad of Downal Baun, ND., TDS w/a - 3
    - PC (NP), introduction to book, A Note on Three Plays, ND., TD - 2
    - PC (NP), Article, Old Erin Poses for Her Portrait, 3-17-29, TD - 4
    - PC (NP), introduction written as a letter to T.H.K., April 1910., PD - 2
    - PC (NP), article, A Dublin Letter, 2-15-36., Tearsheet from SR, - 1
    - PC (NP), poem, Calen 0 Costure Me, 8-3-57., Clipping - 1
    - PC (NP), review of O'Connor's The Times I've Seen, 4-464, Xerox of tearsheet from SR - 1
    - Clippings etc. about, -, 11
  - CONNOLLY, JAMES B. [Listings of Connolly letters are on white cards inside folders]: (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Connolly, J.B. to JAH, 1922-45
    - Connolly, J.B. to JAH, 1946-48 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Connolly, J.B. to JAH, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Connolly, J.B. to JAH, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Connolly, J.B. to JAH, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Connolly, J.B. to JAH, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Connolly, J.B. to JAH, 1953-54 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Connolly, J.B. to JAH, 1955-56 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - CONNOLLY, J.B. ON ANN CONNOLLY (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Connolly, J.B. (B), biographical sketch of Ann Connolly, 2-13-51., TD w/a - 2
  - CONNOLLY, J.B.: PHOTOS (Box 3, Folder 41)
    Ca. 30 photos (some duplicates) [see Photograph File]
  - CONNOLLY, J.B.: CLIPPINGS, (1) (Box 3, Folder 42)
    Ca. 50 clippings
  - CONNOLLY, J.B.: CLIPPINGS, (2) (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - CONNOLLY, J.B.: MISCELLANY (Box 4, Folder 44)
    Ca. 60 miscellaneous items, copies of letters, passport, etc.
  - CONNOLLY, J.B: CLIPPINGS RE (Box 4, Folder 45)
    Ca. 50 clippings etc.
  - CONOR, WILLIAM (Box 4, Folder 46)